About me

Name Gabriel Claramunt

Email <u>Gabriel.claramunt@gmail.com</u>
Blog https://blog.scalents.com/
Github https://github.com/gclaramunt

I have 20 years of experience in software development, architecture, and design.

Experienced in functional programming in Scala for big data systems.

Worked in requirements, OO Analysis and Design, architectural design, development, and optimization of application systems in various domains like Financial Services, Insurance, and Retail. Worked in the Latin America, Caribbean, and North America regions.

Experience

Scalents Qume Inc.

May. 2019 – present Building the World's Fastest

Crypto Derivatives Exchange

http://qume.io

Scalents Principal consultant

Oct. 2017 – present I've executed a variety of projects, consulting on Scala,

Functional Programming, data ingest pipelines, scalable

backends, and JVM optimization.

Starbucks FP Lead (contractor - remote)

Oct. 2016 -Oct. 2017 Working on the new Unified commerce platform, doing design

and coding of customer event flows with kafka, akka streams,

cassandra and aws.

Functional programming/Scala guidance to the group.

Google SW developer – (contractor – remote)

Jul. 2015 – Oct. 2016 loT project for Alphabet Inc. Company

Design and development of a high reliability and scalable messaging and routing service with Scala and Google cloud **Google's Advanced Technology & Projects - Project ARA**Performance optimization for web store project – Java/Spring

Morgan Stanley SW developer – (contractor – onsite)

May 2014 - Jun 2015 End of Day Risk Calculation Engine (RICE) for Interest Rate

Derivatives / Fixed Income Division team

Working on the new End of Day Risk Calculation Engine (RICE) for Interest Rate Derivatives / Fixed Income Division team, I was

responsible of optimization of the RiCE Scala code.

Rewrote the post processing steps of workflow to distribute it in the custom grid services framework achieving a ten-fold reduction in post processing time and a 25% reduction of total processing time, while optimizing the memory profile, allowing to

increase business volume without memory failures.

Optimized the serialization/deserialization of internal application objects to halve the memory usage. Acted as the team's Scala referent, and worked on the evolution of various parts of the

system.

Autodesk Working with Globant offshore team, was the architect for

Oct 2013 - Apr 2014

development of Buzzsaw-A360 adapter, a cloud message bus integration of a legacy file storage using Scala and akka actors. Defined the technical solution, coded the critical use cases and gave guidance and help to the other members of the team.

Independent contractor OLAP database over spark proof of concept for San Francisco Jun 2012 -Sep 2013 startup

Precog

Nov 2012 - May 2013

Startup developing a whole new platform and query language for big data analytics.

Working remotely as integration engineer, owning the client libraries for the REST API and creation of import tools from sql, mongo, and twitter in heavily functional Scala with Scalaz.

Globant

Oct 2010 - Oct 2012

Software Developer - Big Data and High Performance Studio

Autodesk

Configuration module for a cloud based services coordinator and executor. Using Scala and Lift to provide a friendly UI for the configuration web services.

Loyal3

Worked in the final stage of the core Loyal3 CSOP product building before launch. Wrote UI screens with Lift's CSS transformations, core logic in Scala, storage/retrieval of data from mongoDB, unit and functional tests with cucumber-like implementation.

K12

As a remote contractor for K12Inc development team, was part of the core backend group of their courses authoring system.

TCS USA

May 2005 - Aug 2010

(SW developer - onsite)

Working as lead developer / software architect, analyzed the problem with business experts, designed an architecture to satisfy the functional and non-functional requirements, coded and unit tested the critical components in collaboration with the whole team. Acted as a Lead developer/coordinator for off-site teams.

Recognized among the TOP 1% Java developers of my company

For **The Home Depot**:

Designed and leaded a team building a web application deployed in more than 2000 stores of the second biggest retailer in the US. End users love it and it was highlighted in investment analyst reports. Created and evolved an architecture now used in a family of applications. Wrote a low level XLS processing library based on Apache POI but capable of reading and writing

files bigger than 100Mb fast and with a significantly smaller memory footprint. Rewrote a group of Java batch process to get

a 10 times increase in execution speed.

For Motorola Networks:

Using JSF and Java, design and coding of configuration module

for a workflow system.

TCS Uruguay SW developer.

Oct 2002 – May 2005 Worked in multiple projects as a lead developer.

Hista Intl. Consultant in Rational tools and OOAD with UML, RUP, Use

Oct 1999 – Oct 2001 cases and Software architecture, and lead developer for

software development practice in Latin America and the

Caribbean

Education

2012 - 2013 Functional programming, Formal program construction, Category

theory - University of the Republic (UDELAR)

1994 – 1999 Computer Analyst – University of the Republic (UDELAR)

Skills

Programming languages Scala, Java, Haskell, C++, Python

Presentations

PNWScala 2014 What every (Scala) programmer should know about category

theory

https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W67LYX 1J M

flatMap(Oslo) 2018 The (un?) reasonable effectiveness of mathematics in computer

programming

http://2018.flatmap.no/talks/claramunt

ScaleByTheBay 2018 Swimming in the stream

https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gGXa1zOtZTI

Scala reggen (a recursion schemes experiment) https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FT0yDU3UL6g

Organizer

ScaLATAM - First Latin Organizer / Presenter

American conference on Scala and functional

programming

Montevideo Scala

Meetup

Organizer